A Guide to the Edgemont Farm Papers 1925-1998
Digital Library and Archive, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Digital Library and Archive, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Edgemont Farm Papers 1925-1998
Digital Library and Archive, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Ms2003-022
2 containers; 1.0 cu. ft.
Edgemont Farm record books, papers, and correspondence relating to the history, operations, and sale of Edgemont Farm in Halifax County, Virginia, and to the Barksdale and Hutcheson families, former owners of the farm. The collection includes correspondence between John R. Hutcheson and T. B. Hutcheson, Jr., as well as other correspondence of Thomas B. Hutcheson, Jr.; maps, correspondence, and Deed of Trust with David Barksdale regarding the sale of the farm.
The Edgemont Farm Papers were donated to the Digital Library and Archives in 2003.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open to research.
Biographical/Historical Information
According to John R. Hutcheson's farm history, "Edgemont Farm" (Folder 1), the history of Edgemont Farm is somewhat typical of what has happened on many plantations in Southside Virginia. The farm got its name when Thomas Edmunds Barksdale and his wife, Sarah Catherine Edmunds, bought 1000 acres of fertile land on the Dan River near the Southern Railroad known as Barksdales Station and established a farm there in 1851.
The farm remained in the Barksdale family and eventually was passed down through Mary Claiborne Barksdale who married Robert Francis Hutcheson to their sons, Thomas Barksdale Hutcheson and John Redd Hutcheson. After the death of Thomas B. Hutcheson in 1950, the farm was owned by Rosalie S. Hutcheson, his wife, and John R. Hutcheson. Supervision of the farm was under John R. Hutcheson with the assistance of T. B. Hutcheson, Jr., son of Rosalie Hutcheson, and the resident manager of the farm. In 1962, supervision of the farm was turned over to T. B. Hutcheson, Jr. The farm eventually was sold to David Barksdale.
John Redd Hutcheson (V.P.I. class of 1907, M.S., 1909) was the ninth president of Virginia Polytechnic Institute (1945-1947). He also served as director of the Agricultural Extension Division (1919-1944) and chancellor (1947-1955). Thomas Barksdale Hutcheson (V.P.I. class of 1906) was professor of Agronomy (1914-1945) and dean of Agriculture at V.P.I.. Hutcheson Hall at Virginia Tech was named for the brothers, John R. and T. B. Hutcheson. Thomas Barksdale Hutcheson, Jr., (V.P.I. class of 1950) was professor of Agronomy (1964-1968) and head of the Agronomy Department.
Scope and Content Information
Scope is 1925-1998, bulk 1935-1978. Historical materials include John R. Hutcheson's essay "Edgemont Farm," information on Thomas E. Barksdale, maps, and a statement regarding the real estate on Edgemont Farm. Much of the T. B. Hutcheson, Jr., correspondence with John R. Hutcheson is regarding farm operations. Correspondence also relates to T. B. Hutcheson's professional career, and there are materials regarding the naming of Virginia Tech's Hutcheson Hall for John R. and T. B. Hutcheson. Farm record books include cash books, order books, ledgers, and a journal of farm operations, as well as extensive correspondence regarding David Barksdale's purchase of the farm.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged chronologically.
Contents List
- Edgemont Farm Papers 1935-73
  - Edgemont Farm History 1951-62 (Box-folder 1-1)
  - T. B. Hutcheson, Jr., correspondence with J. R. Hutcheson 1925-61 (Box-folder 1-2)
  - T. B. Hutcheson, Jr., correspondence with J. R. Hutcheson 1962-69 (Box-folder 1-3)
  - T. B. Hutcheson, Jr., correspondence 1956-60 (Box-folder 1-4)
  - T. B. Hutcheson, Jr., correspondence 1960-77 (Box-folder 1-5)
  - Maps 1937 (Box-folder 1-6)
  - Term Problem for Agronomy Problems and Soil Management 1949 (Box-folder 1-7)
  - Social Security 1960 (Box-folder 1-8)
  - Mortgage Application and Tax Returns 1961-76 (Box-folder 1-9)
  - Farm Production Sheets, Notes, and Newsletters 1962-78 (Box-folder 1-10)
  - Transfer of Operations 1976-77 (Box-folder 1-11)
  - Sale of Farm 1976-78 (Box-folder 1-12)
  - David Barksdale Deed of Trust and Correspondence 1977-1998 (Box-folder 1-13)
  - Farm Record Book 1935-52 (Box-folder 2-14)
  - Cash Book 1953-55 (Box-folder 2-15)
  - Cash Book 1956-59 (Box-folder 2-16)
  - Cash Book 1959-61 (Box-folder 2-17)
  - Order Book 1962-66 (Box-folder 2-18)
  - Journal, Farm Operations 1962-67 (Box-folder 2-19)
  - Ledger 1967-70 (Box-folder 2-20)
  - Cash Book 1968-73 (Box-folder 2-21)
  - Expenditures 1974-77 (Box-folder 2-22)